Inventory of the John Boyd Bentley Papers, 1895-1987
Earl Gregg Swem Library, College of William and Mary
Special Collections, Earl Gregg Swem Library, College of William and Mary
John Boyd Bentley Papers, 1895-1987
Special Collections, Earl Gregg Swem Library, College of William and Mary
Mss. 82 B44
1,042 items.
Personal and professional papers, 1895-1987, of Bishop John Boyd Bentley.
John Boyd Bentley,; Elvira Carr Bentley,; William Archer Rutherford Goodwin,; Henry Knox Sherrill.
Administrative Information
Restrictions on Access
Collection is open to all researchers.
Acquisition Information
Gift: Acc. No. 82-36; 5 items, 10/2/1982.
Gift: Acc. No. 82-39; 310 items, 10/17/1982.
Gift: Acc. No. 83-22; 350 items, 4/16/1983.
Gift: Acc. No. 84-8; 15 items, 2/9/1984.
Gift: Acc. No. 85-52; 350 items, 11/18/1985.
Gift: Acc. No. 88-10; 2 items, 2/17/1988.
Gift: Acc. No. 88-16; 9 items, 4/26/1988.
Transferred: Acc. No. 94-90; 1 item, 12/21/1994.
Biographical/Historical Information
John Boyd Bentley was born in Hampton, Virginia 9 February 1896. He attended the College of William and Mary and served in the U. S. Field Artillery in World War I. Bentley attended the Virginia Theological Seminary in Alexandria, Virginia He served as an Episcopal clergyman in Alaska and in Williamsburg. He then served as Suffragan Bishop and Bishop of Alaska. From 1947 to 1964, Bentley was Director of Overseas Missions of the Episcopal Church. He died 12 June 1989.
Biography Timeline
1896, February 9 Born, Hampton, Virginia, son of Charles Headley Bentley and Susan Elizabeth (Cake) Bentley
1915 Entered College of William and Mary
(attended 1915-1916 and 1920-1921 but did not graduate)
1917 Entered service in U.S. Field Artillery
1921, May 28 Married Elvira Wentworth Carr(died, 1983)
1921 Attended Theological Seminary in Alexandria, Virginia
1921-1925 Episcopal clergyman in Alaska
1926-1930 Episcopal clergyman in Williamsburg, Virginia
1931 Ordained Bishop in Denver, Colorado
1931-1942 Suffragan Bishop of Alaska
1942-1947 Bishop in charge of Alaska
1947-1964 Director of Overseas Missions of Episcopal Church
1964 Retired and moved to Hampton, Virginia
1964-1989 Episcopal minister in Diocese of Southern Virginia
1989, June 12 Died, Hampton, Virginia.
Scope and Content Information
Personal and professional papers, 1896-1987, of Bishop John Boyd Bentley, Bishop of Alaska and Director of Overseas Missions for the Protestant Episcopal Church and personal papers, 1895-1983, of his wife Elvira Carr Bentley.
Includes comprehensive records of his ministerial career including records of his official acts and texts of sermons and invocations. There is some correspondence relating to Bentley's career, including letters from W. A. R. Goodwin (1869-1939), Rector of Bruton Parish Church, Williamsburg, Virginia; Peter Trimble Rowe (1856-1941), Bishop of Alaska; and Henry Knox Sherrill (1890-1980), President Bishop of the Episcopal Church.
There is material relating to Bentley's work in Alaska, including a series of letters to his wife, 1930-1937, describing his travels on the Alaskan frontier. The collection also includes a photograph collection as well as diaries, correspondence, and photographs which chronicle his tours of the Far East in 1949; a world tour, 1959-1960; and tours of Latin America, 1960-1961. There are audio-cassettes of his autobiography.
Arrangement
Organization
This collection is organized into 7 series. Series 1 contains papers and correspondence; Series 2 contains bound volumes and other related material; Series 3 contains photographs; Series 4 contains overiszed material; Series 5 contains artifacts; Series 6 contains audio tapes; Series 7 contains the addition to the collection.
Arrangement
This collection is arranged by chronologically by date. Series 1: Papers and Correspondence, is further divided into the following subseries: genealogical material, the papers of John Boyd Bentley, and the papers of Elvira Carr Bentley.
Additional Descriptive Data
Separated Material
Books received with the John Boyd Bentley Papers have been removed and relocated within the Manuscript and Rare Books Department, Swem Library, College of William and Mary.
The New England Primer. Boston: Printed by Edward Draper, 1777.
McGuffey's Eclectic Primer. Newly Revised. Cincinnati: Sargent, Wilson & Hinkle, n.d.
Willson, Marcius. The First Reader of the Second Family Series. New York: Harper & Bromers, Publishers, 1860.
My pretty country Picture Book of lane, and lake hill, and brook. London: T. Nelson and sons, n. d.
Confederate Memorial Day. Hampton: Hampton Weekly News Press, 1894.
Freeman, Douglas Southall. R. E. Lee: A biography. 4 volumes. New York: Charles Scribner's Sons, 1934-1935.Inscribed by the last surviving member of Lee's staff.
Pershing, John J. My Experiences In The World War. 2 volumes. New York: Fredrick A. Stokes Company, 1931.Inscribed by Gen. Pershing.
Bruton Parish Churchyard and Church: A guide to the Tombstones, Monuments, and Mural Tablets. Williamsburg, VA: Bruton Parish Church, 1976.Dedicated to Bishop Bentley; inscribed by the Rev. Cotesworth Pinckney Lewis, Rector.
Index Terms
Persons:
Bentley, Elvira Carr, d. 1983.; Goodwin, William Archer Rutherford, 1869-1939.; Sherrill, Henry Knox, Bp., 1890-
Subjects:
Episcopal Church- -Clergy.; Episcopal Church-- Missions.
Geographical Names:
Alaska--History--1867- 1959.; Latin America--Description and travel.
Components List
  Series 1: Papers and Correspondence
- Papers and Correspondence, 1896-1987. (Box 1-2)
  - Genealogical Material. (Box-folder 1:1-3)
    - Genealogical material on Bentley family and ancestral families: Headley, Bull, and Boyd, including photocopies of commissions and papers of family revolutionary war veterans., 19 items. (Box-folder 1:1)
    - Genealogical material on Wood and Cake families, including several copies of Bishop Bentley's The Cake Family: A Bibliographical Memorandum, and other computations of information., 5 items. (Box-folder 1:2)
    - Genealogical material, including notes and family correspondence related to compilation of Bishop Bentley's The Cake Family: A Biographical Memorandum, 1965-1966., 29 items. (Box-folder 1:3)
  - John Boyd Bentley Papers, 1896-1987. (Box 1-2)
    - Bishop Bentley's personal correspondence, 1917-1981., 44 items. (Box-folder 1:4)
      Including letters and postcards to his parents from France during World War I, letters from French citizens, personal letters thanking him for ministerial services, letters from Giles Buckner Cooke (1838-1937) (last surviving member of R. E. Lee's staff) found (with photo of Cook) in Bentley's copy of D.S. Freeman's R. E. Lee, Volume I.
      See also correspondence of Elvira C. Bentley.
    - Bishop Bentley's personal items, 1896-1980., 23 items. (Box-folder 1:5)
      Including birth certificate, school reports, passports, inoculation records, wedding invitation, driver's license (items from personal documents wallet), membership certificates, copy of a poem by Bentley, and copy of will, 1950, of Nancy Jones, for whom Bentley was an legatee.
    - Bishop Bentley's items, relating to his army service, 1971-1928., 41 items. (Box-folder 1:6)
      Including certificates of promotions and training, identity pass for service in France, roster and casualties of Battery B, 111th Field Artillery, a pressed poppy flower from Chateau Thierry, and 5 uniform insignias.
      See also medium oversize file.
    - Bishop Bentley's personal correspondence, 1930-1937., 35 items. (Box-folder 1:7)
      Including letters to Elvira C. Bentley describing his travels and work in the interior of Alaska, especially travel conditions, weather, conditions at missionary posts, and his performance of official acts. Also includes several orders for supplies for mission and undated records of daily temperatures.
    - Bishop Bentley's personal correspondence, 1959-1961., 45 items. (Box-folder 1:8)
      Including letters to Elvira C. Bentley during his world tour of 1959 and tours of Latin America, 1960 and 1961. Descriptions and impressions of London, Paris, Geneva, Israel, several cities in India, Singapore, Thailand, Taipei, Japan, and the Philippines. Includes cursory discussions of church work.
    - Bishop Bentley's correspondence and other items, 1984-1985., 20 items. (Box-folder 1:9)
      Items relate to his receipt of an honorary degree (Doctor of Divinity) from the College of William and Mary, May 1985. Including program and Alumni Gazette.
      See also Medium Oversize file.
    - Bishop Bentley's documents, relating to his personal religious milestones, 1913-1981., 14 items. (Box-folder 1:10)
      Items include baptism certificate, licenses as lay reader and marriage commissioner, certificate as Suffragan Bishop of Alaska, and programs for observation of 50th anniversary of his consecration.
    - Bishop Bentley's biographical information, 1943, 1981., 5 items. (Box-folder 1:11)
      Typed transcript of his oral history interview (September 19, 1981) as part of Columbia University's "Bishop Henry Knox Sherrill Oral History Project". Bentley discusses his own career, missions and missionary work, and Bishop Sherrill. Also a 1 page resume written ca. 1943.
    - Bishop Bentley's correspondence, 1925-1974., 75 items. (Box-folder 1:12)
      Items relate to his ministerial career, including extensive correspondence in 1930-1931 and 1937 among Bentley, Bishop P. T. Rowe, and W. A. R. Goodwin regarding Bentley's appointment(s) in Alaska, Williamsburg area in the 1920's, letters from Bishop Rowe discussing work in Alaska, extensive correspondence with Bishop Henry K. Sherrill regarding Bentley's appointment as director of overseas missions, and correspondence relating to Bentley's nomination as Suffragan Bishop of Southern Virginia (1958).
    - Bishop Bentley's correspondence, 1947., 85 items. (Box-folder 1:13)
      Items include letters congratulating Bishop Bentley on his appointment as Directory of Overseas Missions, including letters from missions around the world.
    - Letters congratulating Bentley on the 25th anniversary of his consecration as Bishop, 1956., 9 items. (Box-folder 1:14)
      See also bound volume of letters.
    - Bishop Bentley's correspondence, 1963-1966., 27 items. (Box-folder 1:15)
      Items are in regards to his retirement as Director of Overseas Missions; letters received from missions and church officials around the world, together with carbon copies of Bentley's acknowledgments.
      See also bound volume of letters received and Medium Oversize file.
    - Letters congratulating Bentley on the 50th anniversary of his consecration as Bishop, 1981., 133 items. (Box-folder 1:16)
      Items include Bentley's list of letters, gifts, etc., received and date acknowledged.
    - Bishop Bentley's papers, 1964-1984, 22 items. (Box-folder 1:17)
      Items include programs and bulletins from church services, historical observances and ceremonies in which Bishop Bentley participated, including bulletin of 1984 William and Mary commencement ceremony.
    - Bishop Bentley's papers, 1933-1970., 10 items. (Box-folder 1:18)
      Items include addresses at commencement ceremonies, dedications, ordinations, memorial services, and historical society meetings, 1933-1970, including comments on duties of priests, missionary work, and historical events.
    - Bishop Bentley's papers, 1971-1979, 17 items. (Box-folder 1:19)
      Items include addresses at ordinations, memorial services, and historical observances, 1971-1979, including outline of 1975 address entitled "Williamsburg As I Knew It."
    - Bishop Bentley's papers, including sermons, 1927-1932., 10 items. (Box-folder 1:20)
      Most items handwritten, a few typed, including record of occasions on which each was delivered; arranged chronologically, according to date first delivered.
    - Bishop Bentley's sermons, 1934-1948., 13 items. (Box-folder 1:21)
      Items include records of occasions on which they were delivered; arranged according to date first delivered.
    - Bishop Bentley's sermons and remarks at services delivered primarily at churches in Hampton and the Virginia Peninsula, 1959-1973., 8 items. (Box-folder 1:22)
      Arranged by date delivered.
    - Bishop Bentley's record of sermons and addresses delivered primarily in Southern Virginia, 1965-1985., 1 item. Typed on 126 pages from looseleaf notebook. (Box-folder 1:23)
      Arranged by place and date, specifying occasion and text used.
    - Bishop Bentley's "Appointments Completed," 1964-1978., 1 item. 159 pages. (Box-folder 1:24)
      Comprehensive calendar/schedule of daily activities, including official acts, meetings, addresses, and invocations, including record of miles traveled and expenses incurred on his travels, mostly on the Virginia peninsula.
    - Bishop Bentley's copies of annual and monthly (tabular) reports of "Official Acts," 1964-1969., 5 items. (Box-folder 1:25)
      Official acts include baptisms, confirmations, marriages, etc. that he performed in Diocese of Southern Virginia.
      Arranged chronologically, grouped by year.
    - Bishop Bentley's copies of annual and monthly (tabular) reports of official acts; and a tabulation and geographical breakdown of these acts, 1922-1985., 13 items. (Box-folder 1:26)
      Copies of annual and monthly (tabular) reports of official acts which he performed in Diocese of Southern Virginia, 1970-1978, 1985; and a tabulation and geographical breakdown of official acts performed, 1922- 1976.
    - Bishop Bentley's records of baptisms which he performed during his ministerial career, 1922-1987., 2 items. 211 pages. (Box-folder 2:1)
      Items are from a loose-leaf notebook detailing names, dates, and places of services.
    - Bishop Bentley's records of consecration, ordinations, and marriages performed during career, 1922-1983., 9 items. 61 pages. (Box-folder 2:2)
      Items are from a loose-leaf notebook(s) detailing names, dates, and place for each act, including occasional related correspondences.
    - Bishop Bentley's papers including record of burial services performed during career, 1922-1987., 13 items. 127 pages. (Box-folder 2:3)
      Items are from a loose-leaf notebook detailing names, dates, and places of services. Also includes occasional funeral home records and newspaper obituaries.
    - Bishop Bentley's papers including records of confirmations performed during ministerial career, 1931-1966., 14 items. 166 pages. (Box-folder 2:4)
      Pages from a loose-leaf notebook detailing names, dates, and places of services, plus records of confirmations performed on his East Asian travels.
    - Bishop Bentley's papers including record of confirmations performed during ministerial career, 1967-1985., 14 items. 189 pages. (Box-folder 2:5)
      Pages from a loose-leaf notebook detailing names, dates, and places of services.
    - Bishop Bentley's papers including items relating to his trip to Far East (1948-9) and his world tour of 1959; 1948-1959., 8 items. (Box-folder 2:6)
      Items include travel diaries of both trips, documents pertaining to honorary degree received in Japan (December 1948), and itinerary for 1959 tour.
      See also travel diary of Elvira C. Bentley for the 1959 trip and Medium Oversize subseries.
    - Bishop Bentley's writings, 1916, 1931-46., 13 items. (Box-folder 2:7)
      Items include Blackbeard (a story) in March 1916 The William and Mary Literary Magazine, and 12 articles on his adventures and travels in The Alaskan Churchman.
    - Bishop Bentley's papers including newspaper and magazine clippings on personal matters., 12 items. (Box-folder 2:8)
      Items especially concern his army service, and high school football team and re-unions, and a copy of wedding announcement.
    - Newspaper and magazine clippings, 1927-1970., 42 items. (Box-folder 2:9)
      Items regard Bentley's professional career, including articles on his appointments, many describing his work in Alaska and his retirement. Also includes a 1927 article by Bentley, entitled With the Episcopal Students at the College of William and Mary, and the December 1956 issue of The Alaskan Churchman.
  - Elvira Carr Bentley Papers, 1895-1983. (Box-folder 2:10-13)
    - Personal items of Elvira C. Bentley, 1895-1983., 13 items. (Box-folder 2:10)
      Items include a birth certificate, passports, inoculation certificates, social security card (items from wallet), obituary, death certificate, and description of her death by her husband, and items relating to retirement and death of her father.
    - Personal items of Elvira C. Bentley, 1914-1953., 13 items. (Box-folder 2:11)
      Items include all materials related to her education, high school graduation memorabilia, membership certificate of Colonial Dames, copy of address given in Atlantic City (1934) and her diary of 1949 Far East trip.
      See also Medium Oversize File.
    - Personal correspondence of Elvira C. Bentley, 1921-?, n.d., 14 items. (Box-folder 2:12)
      Item mostly concern undated letters received from Bentley family and friends in Alaska, and silver anniversary cards received.
    - Personal letters of Elvira Carr Bentley received from Bishop P. T. Rowe, 1921-1941., 21 items. (Box-folder 2:13)
      Most letters were received during his trips to East Coast and during Bishop Bentley's absence; discusses church financial troubles during the Depression, her work with women's church organizations in Alaska, and Rowe's expectation that Bentley will succeed him; includes letter from Mrs. Vernon M. Geddy on behalf of the "Bishop Bentley Branch of the Women's Auxiliary of the Bruton Parish Church" (10 February 1934) inquiring how they can assist work in Alaska and Rowe's letter (5 December 1935) describing his visit to Williamsburg and Hampton.
  Series 2: Bound Volumes and Related Material
- Bound Volumes and Related Material, 1873-1986. (Box-folder 2:14-24)
  - Account book of C. D. Cake, (Bentley's grandfather), Hampton, Virginia, March-November 1873., 40 pages. MsV 1. (Box-folder 2:14)
    Record of purchases for construction projects; originally a pocket diary for 1871, but never used for this purpose.
  - Commonplace book of Elvira W. (Carr) Bentley relating to commencement from Hampton High School, 1914., 36 pages. MsV 2. (Box-folder 2:15)
    Includes diary of final weeks before graduation, pressed class flowers, class roster, and other enclosed items which are in a separate folder of her personal items.
  - Photograph album of Hampton and Virginia peninsula, 1914-1915., 144 photographs on 52 pages. Photographs. MsV 3. (Box-folder 2:16)
    Includes labeled photos of ships, harbor, sites of city, Bentley's family and friends, College of William and Mary, and Bentley's handwritten description (ca. 1983) of photos.
  - Commonplace book The Form of Solemnization of Matrimony from the Book of Common Prayer., 13 pages. MsV 4. (Box-folder 2:17)
    Text of wedding service, marriage certificate and signatures of witnesses for Bentley's wedding, 28 May 1921.
  - Photograph album, photos of the "Bishop's Lodge" Nenana, Alaska, 1932-1937, n.d., 29 pages. Photographs. MsV 5. (Box-folder 2:18)
  - Letterbook. Bound volume of letters received on the 25th anniversary of Bentley's consecration as Bishop, 29 September 1956., 53 pages. MsV 6. (Box-folder 2:19)
    See also folder of other letters.
  - Letterbook. Bound volume of letters received upon Bentley's retirement as director of Overseas Missions, 31 October 1964., 104 pages. MsV 7. (Box-folder 2:20)
    See other letters in Manuscript Folder.
  - Guest book for 50th anniversary of Bentley's consecration as Bishop, St. John's Church, [Hampton, Virginia], 29 September 1981., 18 pages. MsV 8. (Box-folder 2:21)
  - Additional correspondence, including letters of greetings and congratulation from House of Bishops and from Diocese of Southern Virginia, 1986., 3 items. (Box-folder 2:22)
  - Miscellaneous items found inside a 1976 book, Bruton Parish Churchyard and Church: A Guide to the Tombstones, Monuments, and Mural Tablets, dedicated to Bentley., 4 items. (Box-folder 2:23)
    Items include updated newspaper description of book, note cards of remarks at dedication of book, and transcription of tombstone in Hampton, Virginia.
  - Outline and first 107 handwritten pages of Bentley's reminiscences, John Boyd Bentley, His Life and Times: An Autobiography., 2 items. (Box-folder 2:24)
  Series 3: Photographs
- Photographs, 1898-1985. (Box-folder 3:1-22)
  - Photographs: Cake family portrait (1898), childhood photos of Bentley and photos relating to Bentley's military service, 1898-1919. (Box-folder 3:1)
    See also mounted photographs and medium oversize items and 4 army photos, in oversize file.
  - Photographs: wedding pictures of Elvira C. Bentley, pictures of first stint in Alaska, and Bentley in Williamsburg and Hampton, Virginia, 1919-1930. (Box-folder 3:2)
    See also mounted photographs.
  - Official photos of Bentley and others upon his consecration as Bishop, 1931. (Box-folder 3:3)
    See also negatives file.
  - Photographs of Alaska and portraits of Bentley (1935), 1931-1935. (Box-folder 3:4)
  - Photographs of damage at Buckroe Beach, Hampton, Virginia, in the aftermath of the hurricane of 1933. (Box-folder 3:5)
  - Photographs of Alaska and portraits of Bentley (1939), 1935-1939. (Box-folder 3:6)
  - Photographs of Alaska, 1942-1947. (Box-folder 3:7)
  - Photographs of the Bentleys in Alaska, Ca. 1931-1947, n.d. (Box-folder 3:8)
  - Photographs of people in Alaska, especially at St. Mark's Mission, Nenana, Alaska, Ca. 1931-1947, n.d. (Box-folder 3:9)
  - Photographs of Alaska, especially of St. Mark's Mission, Nenana, Alaska, Ca. 1931-1947, n.d. (Box-folder 3:10)
    See also postcards and mounted photo album in bound manuscript volumes.
  - Photographs of Alaska; ships and natural scenery, Ca. 1931-1947, n.d. (Box-folder 3:11)
    See also postcards.
  - Photographs - portraits of Bentley and photos of Bentleys on Far East tour of 1949; 1948-1949. (Box-folder 3:12)
  - Photographs of Japan and Philippines taken on Far East tour, 1949. (Box-folder 3:13)
    See also postcard folder.
  - Photographs of Bentley and others at Bishop's Conference, ca. 1954; of party celebrating Bentley's 25th anniversary of his consecration (1956); of Bishop Henry K. Sherrill; and of Bentley on his 1959 world tour, 1954-1959. (Box-folder 3:14)
  - Photographs of Bentley's home in Hampton, photos taken on and after Bentley's retirement, photos of Bentley receiving award from the College of William and Mary (1970), and pictures of family and friends enclosed in correspondence, 1962-1981. (Box-folder 3:15)
  - Photographs of painted portrait of Bentley during his service in Alaska, and photographs at 1985 William and Mary Commencement, at which Bentley received an honorary degree, 1981-1985. (Box-folder 3:16)
  - Photographs of Bentley and Mrs. Bentley, including several autographed visa/passport photos found in Bentley's travel documents wallet, Ca. 1947-1964, n.d. (Box-folder 3:17)
  - Photographs: carte de visite and mounted photographs of Bentley's family, 19th century. (Box-folder 3:18)
  - Photographs, mounted, of Hampton Harbor and 1912 Hampton High School football team, 1908-1912. (Box-folder 3:19)
    See also photograph album in bound manuscript volumes and newspaper clippings.
  - Photographs (mounted) and postcards of Bentley's family and, especially, of Bentley's military service, 1916-1922. (Box-folder 3:20)
    See also oversize file.
  - Mounted photographs of Alaska and Elvira C. Bentley in Alaska (1921-1925), and negatives of photos from Bentley's (1931) consecration, 1921-1925, 1931. (Box-folder 3:21)
  - Postcards of Alaska and postcards of Japan (with original wrapping), n.d. (Box-folder 3:22)
  Series 4: Oversize
- Oversize, 1914-1985.
  - Medium Oversize, 1914-1985.